{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man was forced to begin his most famous campaign after his compatriots launched a drunken raid on settlements by the Salmon River. This leader was able to escape the clutches of Samuel Sturgis at the Battle of Canyon Creek, even though he was betrayed by the Crow tribe. After Oliver Howard captured this man at the Battle of Bear Paw Mountain, this leader said that he “will fight no more forever.” For ten points, name this chief of the Nez Perce who attempted to lead his tribe to Canada.",
      "answer": "Chief Joseph"
    },
    {
      "question": "This treaty was the target of the bull Zelo Domus Dei, in which Pope Innocent X declared it “empty of meaning and effect for all time.” This treaty guaranteed free navigation on the Rhine and reaffirmed the principle of cuius regio, eius religio laid out in the Peace of Augsburg. The Eighty Years’ War was ended as a result of this treaty, which combined negotiations at Osnabruck and Munster. For ten points, name this peace treaty that ended the Thirty Years War.",
      "answer": "Peace of Westphalia"
    },
    {
      "question": "This philosopher rejected that humans have a real notion of self in formulating his “bundle theory.” This thinker, who wrote a massively successful History of England, originated a problem sometimes called his “guillotine,” the Is-Ought problem. This author of “Of Miracles” divided statements into “relations of ideas” and “matters of fact.” A “missing shade of blue” was imagined by, for ten points, what Scottish philosopher who wrote An Enquiry Concerning Human Understanding?",
      "answer": "David Hume"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s most famous endeavor was thwarted by Executive Order 1111, which placed his officers under federal control. After this man refused to listen to Attorney General Nicholas Katzenbach, he was confronted by Henry Graham when John F. Kennedy called up the National Guard. This man opposed James Hood and Vivian Malone at the Foster Auditorium after declaring his support for “segregation forever.” For ten points, name this governor of Alabama who made the “stand in the schoolhouse door” in 1963.",
      "answer": "George Wallace"
    },
    {
      "question": "A German territory in what is now this country was governed by Ambrosius Ehinger, who was employed by the Welser banking family. The British Legions under Miguel de la Torre lost to Jose Antonio Paez, who led this nation’s forces at the Battle of Carabobo. Simon Bolivar’s Decree of War to the Death primarily pertained to this country. For ten points, name this South American country that gained independence after the Battle of Lake Maracaibo.",
      "answer": "Venezuela"
    },
    {
      "question": "This piece in C minor, which opens with a dominant seventh chord followed by loud descending runs of sixteenth notes, was dedicated to “his friend Franz Liszt.” The event that inspired this work caused its composer to lament “All this has caused me much pain. Who could have forseen it?”; that event, the failing of the 1831 November Uprising, crushed hopes for freedom in its composer’s native Poland. For ten points, name this work for solo piano, an etude [ay-tood] by Frederic Chopin [sho-pan].",
      "answer": [
        "Revolutionary Etude or Etude on the Bombardment of Warsaw",
        "Etude Opus 10, Number 12"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "At the 1205 Battle of Adrianople, this man led a force that joined Baldwin the I of the Latin Empire to fight Tsar Kaloyan of the Bulgars. Michael Comnenus may have ordered the blinding of this man, and his daughter Anna married the king of Serbia, Stefan Nemanjic. This man, who introduced the silver grosso as currency in Venice, joined crusaders at the St. Mark’s Basilica. Isaac II was replaced with Alexius Angelus in the Fourth Crusade by, for ten points, what blind Doge of Venice?",
      "answer": "Enrico Dandolo"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this battle, Everett Peabody lost his life trying to hold off oncoming Confederates that other Union commanders were unable to detect. Benjamin Prentiss was one of the Union commanders at this battle, where Don Carlos Buell separated his Army of the Ohio into four divisions. P.G.T. Beauregard took command of the Confederate troops after Albert Sidney Johnston became the highest ranking officer to die in the Civil War in, for ten points, what 1862 battle where heavy fighting took place along the Hornet’s Nest in Tennessee?",
      "answer": "Battle of Shiloh"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this city, the Fortaleza do Monte overlooks the remains of a church whose facade was constructed by Japanese Christians under Carlo Spinola. Following a Dutch East India Company attack on this city in 1622, the Guia Fortress was built. The Bridge of Friendship is one of three bridges connecting parts of this city, where reclamation projects connected the islands of Coloane and Taipa. For ten points, name this special administrative region in the Pearl River Delta alongside Hong Kong, a city that was under Portuguese control until 1999.",
      "answer": "Macau"
    },
    {
      "question": "Much of this state’s La Loma Park was damaged in a 1923 event that began in Wildcat Canyon. A 1990 disaster began in this state’s Santa Ynez Mountains. A Maxine Hong Kingston book details the effects of a 1991 firestorm that killed at least 25 people in this state. The Santa Ana winds have contributed to many natural disasters in this state, including the 1970 Laguna Fire in its south. For ten points, name this state where at least 80 people died in the 2018 Camp Fire.",
      "answer": "California"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A cheese spread made by this civilization was known as Moretum. This civilization built the Barbegal complex to as a watermill to process grain, and they used the Burdigala region to grow wine grapes. Garum was a fish sauce created by this civilization, whose Frumentarii secret service collected wheat. For ten points, name this ancient civilization whose agricultural writings include works by Cato the Elder.",
        "answer": "ancient Rome"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The oldest surviving work of prose in Latin is Cato the Elder’s work on agriculture, which heavily influenced this Roman writer’s ten volume Natural History.",
        "answer": "Pliny the Elder"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire temporarily checked the territorial ambitions of Nikephoros I by winning the Battle of Krasos. The Barmakids were influential during the rule of this dynasty, which suppressed a series of African slave revolts called the zanj. This empire defeated the Tang Dynasty at the Battle of Talas River, although its last ruler al-Musta’sim, was rolled up in a carpet and trampled to death during Hulagu Khan’s 1258 siege of its capital. For ten points, name this Baghdad-based caliphate that succeeded the Umayyad.",
        "answer": "Abbasid Caliphate"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Abbasid caliph Harun al-Rashid founded this library in Baghdad, which became a center of learning for science and the humanities. It was destroyed in the 1258 sack of Baghdad.",
        "answer": "House of Wisdom"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man produced two paintings from the view of Westminster and Waterloo Bridge to offer differing perspectives on the 1834 burning of the houses of Parliament. This man depicted a 98-gun ship being towed to be broken up in his Fighting Temeraire. Another painting by this artist is set on the Maidenhead Bridge and seemingly shows a hare running from a train. For ten points, name this British artist of Rain, Steam, and Speed.",
        "answer": "Joseph Mallord William “J.M.W.” Turner"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Fighting Temeraire was one of the last remaining ships to have fought in this 1805 battle, where she rammed the Redoutable.",
        "answer": "Battle of Trafalgar"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s resignation was commemorated by the Mischianza Party. In an early battle, this man moved his troops across the Verrazzano Narrows shortly before outflanking the Guan Heights. This man resisted an attack at Germantown shortly after winning the Battle of Brandywine. Though he was victorious at Long Island and later captured Philadelphia, this man resigned and was replaced by Henry Clinton. For ten points, name this British commander who was victorious at Bunker Hill.",
        "answer": "William Howe"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In September 1775, William Howe took over command of all British forces in America from this man, who then returned to Britain.",
        "answer": "Thomas Gage"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Giangiacomo Feltrinelli was the first to publish this author’s most famous work after it was smuggled out of its native country. The CIA declassified dozens of documents about its role in supporting that work by this author, which begins with the funeral of the title character’s mother Marya and is interspersed with scenes between the title character and Lara Antipov. This man claimed that leaving Russia would be “tantamount to death” as one of his reasons for declining the 1958 Nobel Prize in Literature. For ten points, name this Russian author of Dr. Zhivago.",
        "answer": "Boris Pasternak"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The CIA pushed for the Nobel Prize to be given to Pasternak, whose work was primarily published in Russia in this underground, illegal form that sought to avoid Soviet censorship.",
        "answer": "Samizdat"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This monarch was crowned under the statute Titulus Regius after ordering the arrest of Earl Rivers. This ruler claimed that his predecessor’s marriage to Elizabeth Woodville was illegitimate and took the throne after supposedly ordering James Tyrell to murder the Princes in the Tower. This man was slain at the Battle of Bosworth Field, making him the final Plantagenet ruler. For ten points, name this king from the House of York during the War of the Roses.",
        "answer": "Richard III"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2012, an excavation discovered Richard III’s remains under a parking lot in this English city.",
        "answer": "Leicester"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Forty seven years before this case, Weeks v. U.S. dealt with the same rule, but only at the federal level. The defendant of this case worked under Shon Birns, a gambling kingpin. The “Fruit of the Poisonous Tree” doctrine was added to the Exclusionary rule that this decision applied to the states. The defendant argued that paraphernalia and books were taken without probable cause in, for ten points, what Fourth Amendment case that outlawed evidence taken from “unreasonable search and seizures?”",
        "answer": "Mapp v. Ohio"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mapp v Ohio applied the Fourth Amendment to the states in a process that involves the 14th Amendment and is known by this term.",
        "answer": [
          "selective incorporation",
          "word forms"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Venetia Burney coined the name of this location, which is home to mountains named for Tenzing Norgay and Edmund Hillary. The discovery of this location used a blink comparator used by Clyde Tombaugh. In a book titled for How I Killed this object and Why it Had it Coming, Michael Brown recounted how this location was reclassified after his discovery of Eris, a trans-Neptunian body. The first Kuiper [kye-per] belt object to be discovered was, for ten points, what dwarf planet that was once classified as the ninth planet from the Sun?",
        "answer": "Pluto"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Astronomer Mike Brown also discovered this dwarf planet, the third largest-known trans- Neptunian object after Pluto and Eris. It takes its name from a Hawaiian goddess.",
        "answer": "Haumea"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Reconstruction",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "US President whose assassination prevented the original plans for Reconstruction.",
          "answer": "Abraham Lincoln"
        },
        {
          "question": "Group of Republicans who pushed for civil rights for former slaves and the impeachment of Andrew Johnson.",
          "answer": "Radical Republicans"
        },
        {
          "question": "President whose controversial election in 1876 ended Reconstruction.",
          "answer": "Rutherford B. Hayes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Democrat who lost the 1876 election.",
          "answer": "Samuel Tilden"
        },
        {
          "question": "Agency led by Oliver Otis Howard that provided aid to former slaves, legendarily including “40 acres and a mule.”",
          "answer": "Freedmen’s Bureau or Bureau of Refugees, Freedmen, and Abandoned Lands"
        },
        {
          "question": "1864 bill outlining re-admittance procedures that was pocket-vetoed by the president.",
          "answer": "Wade-Davis Bill"
        },
        {
          "question": "Oath that would have been required by that bill, forcing its taker to swear he had “never voluntarily borne arms” against the US.",
          "answer": "Ironclad Oath"
        },
        {
          "question": "book.",
          "answer": "Eric Foner"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Ottoman Empire",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital city of the empire, established after the fall of Constantinople.",
          "answer": "Istanbul"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that formed the Hellenic Republic, then a monarchy, after winning independence from the Ottomans in the 1820s.",
          "answer": "Greece"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern country where Muhammad Ali took power from the Ottomans in 1807, shortly after the British left Alexandria.",
          "answer": "Egypt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Infantry unit established in the 14th century whose members were kidnapped young Christians.",
          "answer": "Janissaries"
        },
        {
          "question": "First Sultan of the empire.",
          "answer": "Osman I or Osman Gazi"
        },
        {
          "question": "19th century era of reform that began with the Edict of Gulhane.",
          "answer": "Tanzimat reforms"
        },
        {
          "question": "Palace, now a museum, that was the sultan’s residence and base of the empire’s administration.",
          "answer": "Topkapi Palace"
        },
        {
          "question": "Precursor of the empire, a Seljuk sultanate that controlled Anatolia from the city of Konya.",
          "answer": "Sultanate of Rum"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Philippines",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country that held power over the Philippines until after World War II.",
          "answer": [
            "United States of America",
            "America"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital city whose dialect of Tagalog was defined as a national language in the 20th century.",
          "answer": "Manila"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religion of Cardinal Jaime Sin, who was instrumental in the Philippines’ regime change in 1986.",
          "answer": "Roman Catholicism"
        },
        {
          "question": "President and dictator of the Philippines from 1965 to 1986, when he was overthrown.",
          "answer": "Ferdinand Marcos"
        },
        {
          "question": "1986 campaign of civil resistance that led to the overthrow of that leader.",
          "answer": [
            "People Power Revolution",
            "EDSA Revolution"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Palacethatwasstormedduringthat1986revolution,revealingtheFirstLady’scollectionofthousands of shoes.",
          "answer": "Malacanang Palace"
        },
        {
          "question": "Family that included a senator assassinated in 1983, the first female president of the Philippines, and another president who preceded Rodrigo Duterte.",
          "answer": [
            "Aquino family",
            "Benigno Aquino Jr., Corazon Aquino, and/or Benigno Aquino III"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Name for the Muslim population of the Philippines; a namesake National Liberation Front fought for an autonomous region on Mindanao.",
          "answer": "Moro people"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this war, the Volunteer Army was forced to take the Ice March towards the Kuban region. Two rival governments formed during this war at Omsk and Samara. The (20 pts)",
        "Czechoslovak Legion revolted and controlled most of a railway during this war; another major revolt in this war was launched by sailors at (10 pts)",
        "Kronstadt who were angry at the policies of wartime communism implemented by Leon Trotsky. For ten points, name this war between the Red and White Armies, ending in a Bolshevik triumph."
      ],
      "answer": "Russian Civil War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A 1993 attack on this organization’s headquarters was carried out by Pakistani terrorist Mir Qazi. In a 2003 scandal, Robert Novak revealed that Valerie Plame worked for this organization. Following revelations of his (20 pts)",
        "affair with Paula Broadwell, David Petraeus stepped down as head of this organization, which helped plan an assassination in (10 pts)",
        "Abbottabad, Pakistan carried out by Seal Team Six. The assassination of Osama bin Laden was masterminded by, for ten points, what American agency that engages in covert action overseas?"
      ],
      "answer": "Central Intelligence Agency"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The lands of these people were surveyed by Henry Bulwer, who tried to convince Bartle Frere not to begin a series of annexations. Lord Chelmsford gave these people an ultimatum in order to force them to declare war, a conflict that ended when (20 pts)",
        "Ulundi was burned and king Cetshwayo was sent into exile. These people fought the battles of (10 pts)",
        "Isandlwana and Rorke’s Drift against British forces. For ten points, name this South African ethnic group that was once led by Shaka."
      ],
      "answer": "Zulu Empire"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The longest single story in the Quran re-tells the life of this prophet. The Biblical book named for this prophet is read as haftarah on the afternoon of Yom Kippur. This man, who prophecies to a group of people who “could not tell their right hand from their left,” gets (20 pts)",
        "belligerent after a fast-growing gourd-vine he was using for shade gets eaten by a worm. This prophet tried to (10 pts)",
        "sail to Tarshish to avoid prophesying doom to Nineveh as he was commanded. For ten points, name this Biblical prophet who is swallowed by a huge fish."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Jonah or Jonas",
        "or Yunus"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This location inspired a similar development in Toa Baja, Puerto Rico that was divided into eight sections and numerous sub-sections. Zip code 11756 was given to this location, where documents required that “any person other than a member of the (20 pts)",
        "Caucasian race” could not buy. This location in Nassau County consisted of units that could be (10 pts)",
        "financed with 30-year mortgages that required no down payment. At one point, a house was built every 16 minutes in, for ten points, what “mass-produced” suburb in 1950s New York?"
      ],
      "answer": "Levittown"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This event inspired most of the album The Rising by Bruce Springsteen, including its song “My City of Ruins.” Clear Channel Communications released a memo suggesting that “Imagine” by John Lennon, every song by Rage Against the Machine, and over 100 other songs (20 pts)",
        "not be played on the radio in the wake of this event. Paul McCartney’s single “Freedom” was written after he witnessed this event from the (10 pts)",
        "tarmac of JFK airport in Queens. For ten points, name this terrorist attack that was memorialized by a benefit concert in New York in October 2001."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "September 11th, 2001 attacks",
        "9/11 attacks",
        "2001 World Trade Center attacks and any other specific aspect of the 9/11 attacks"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man ended the revolt of the Obotrites at the battle of Recknitz and secured power after facing a rebellion from Liudolf and Conrad the Red. The creation of the Gero Codex and a scriptorium at Quedlinburg led scholars to name a (20 pts)",
        "“Renaissance” after this man. This man was crowned in 962 by Pope John XII, seven years after a victory over Bulcsu ended (10 pts)",
        "Magyar raids into Western Europe. For ten points, identify this “Great” German Holy Roman Emperor who was victorious at Lechfeld."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Otto the Great",
        "Otto I"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A signatory of the Declaration of Independence from this state named John Witherspoon helped shift the emphasis of one of its universities away from clerical training. A governor of this colony who believed the Stamp Act was justified was an (20 pts)",
        "illegitimate son of Benjamin Franklin named William. Known as the Crossroads of the Revolution, this state is home to a (10 pts)",
        "university attended by James Madison and Aaron Burr; that university shares its name with a nearby 1777 battle. For ten points, name this home state of Princeton University."
      ],
      "answer": "New Jersey"
    }
  ]
}